Guide to the Charles Hamm Collection 2019.004
Brooklyn Historical Society
Charles Hamm Collection
1920-2011
Brooklyn Historical Society
Hamm, Charles J.
2019.004
2.1 Linear Feet in 1 legal size document box, 1 oversize flat box, and 1 folder in flat file
Materials documenting the life and career of Charles Hamm, an advertising executive, bank president and philanthropist. Photographs, awards, collected artwork and items concerning his mother, socialite Lisbeth Higgins Hamm are included.
Biographical
Charles J. Hamm was born in Brooklyn in 1937, the son of Lisbeth Higgins Hamm and Frank Hamm. His childhood home was on Pierrepont Street in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood. He attended Brooklyn Friends School, Packer Collegiate Institute, Berkeley Carroll School, and Polytechnic Preparatory School; all in the borough. He went on to Phillips Exeter Academy and after serving in the Army, he attended Harvard, then received a graduate degree in business at New York University. During his advertising career, Hamm worked for McCann Erickson Worldwide as Executive Vice President and Vice Chairman of their United States division. In 1975, he became Trustee of Independence Community Bank Corporation, then President in 1985. For much of his time with the bank, he and his wife, Irene, lived in Brooklyn Heights. After retiring in the early 2000s, they resided in Mystic, Connecticut and kept an apartment in the Bronxville neighborhood of Manhattan. His board memberships have included Pratt Institute, Brooklyn Botanic Garden, and Brooklyn Academy of Music.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series by type. Items in each series are not arranged.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Charles Hamm in 2019.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes items from the life and career of Charles Hamm and his mother, Lisbeth Higgins Hamm. Photographs are formal and candid, showing the Higgins and Hamm families and various charitable events attended by Charles Hamm. Honors and awards include personal and professional recognitions, as well as Hamm's philanthropic work. Items in the Artwork series were created or collected by the family, including two drawings by Juan De'Prey. This series also inlcudes books highlighting items from Hamm's art collection and his own work. Audiovisual items show Hamm during television appearances and an event at the Brooklyn Historical Society.
Related Materials
Brooklyn schools collection 1985.054
Charles M. Higgins papers 1978.114
The Packer Collegiate Institute records 2014.019
Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Photographs; Maps; Certificates; Brooklyn Heights Seminary (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Art; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Charities |z New York (State) |z New York; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Series I: Drawings and Photographs
  - Mounted Photographs with Clipping, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hand Drawn Map of Brooklyn Heights, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Voices of Harmony, Mounted Photographs, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mounted Photographs, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Photograph, circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Signed Photograph of Lisbeth Higgins Hamm, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Signed Drawing of W.C. Handy, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Photograph, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of ICB Presidents, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photograph of the Brooklyn Bridge (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
- Series II: Honors and Awards
  - Brooklyn Heights Seminary Diploma, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harvard University Club Certificate, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Army Certificate, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Borough President Citation, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Federal Home Loan Bank Certificate, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Historical Society Certificate, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Phillips Exeter Academy Certificate, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Socrates Sculpture Park Note, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - State of New York Banking Department Resolution, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Phillips Exeter Academy Certificate, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Habitat for Humanity Plaque, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Adam's Prize, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Medals (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Artwork
  - Portrait of Charles Hamm by Tom Buechner (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Drawing of Lisbeth Higgins With Dance Partner (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Bird heads Drawn by Charles Hamm (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Ink Drawing of a Truck in the Street for the Charles Higgins Ink Contest (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Colored Pencil Sketch of Lisbeth Higgins (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Oil Painting Portrait of Lisbeth Higgins (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Drawing by Munk (Cabinet CBH, 2, Print Room [Flat file: B, Drawer: 1])
  - Girl with Bike by Juan De'Prey
  - Girl by Juan De'Prey
  - The Art of Life, Commentary and Artworks by Charles J. Hamm, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Costal Art, The Collection of Charles J. and Irene Hamm, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Audiovisual
  - Brooklyn Historical Society Honors Charles Hamm, DVD, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Caucus Up Close with Charles Hamm (Box 2)
  - Independence Community Bank with Charles Hamm, VHS, 2001 (Box 2)